American Congregational Association records, 1846-2022.
Congregational Library & Archives
American Congregational Association records, 1846-2022.
RG4360
Congregational Library & Archives
24.91 Cubic Feet
(32 boxes)
The American Congregational Association was formed in 1851 as the Congregational Library Association. The Association was formally incorporated in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts in 1854. In 1864, the organization changed its name to the American Congregational Association in recognition of its broader scope. In 1857 the Association moved from its rented rooms at the Tremont Temple to a house on Chauncy Street where it remained for ten years. In 1872 the Association purchased the Somerset Building and the library moved into that space in 1874. The Association built the Congregational House in 1898 and once again the library moved into the new building. In 2017 the American Congregational Association sold the Congregational House to Faros Properties and signed a long-term lease to keep the library within its historic home. The American Congregational Association collection covers the four main areas of business of the Association: The Board of Directors, the Finances of the Association, the management of the Association's building portfolio, and the management of the Congregational Library & Archives.
American Congregational Association.
Congregational Christian Historical Society
Congregational Library Association.
Langworthy, Isaac P. (Isaac Pendleton)
Worthley, Harold Field
Restrictions on Access
Except where otherwise stated, this collection is available for researchers only with special permission from the chair of the board or directors of the American Congregational Association and/or from the executive director of the Congregational Library & Archives. Please contact the library directly at ref@14beacon.org to obtain permission to access the collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection is the internal permanent collection of the American Congregational Association, and by relation, the Congregational Library & Archives. Records for this collection have been gathered over the history of Library as part of the Library's records management duties. Additional records have been provided to for inclusion into the collection by board members after they have stepped down from board duties. The collection regularly receives accruals of additional materials.
Accruals
Periodic accruals of records from the board or directors are expected annually. Periodic accruals of certain financial records are expected annually. Additional unplanned accruals of unspecified records are also expected.
Historical Note
The American Congregational Association was formed in 1851 as the Congregational Library Association. Two years later, reorganized and expanded, it rented rooms at the Tremont Street Temple in Boston, with a library of 56 books and pamphlets. The Association was formally incorporated in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts in 1854 "for the purpose of establishing and perpetuating a library of the religious history and literature of New England, and for the erection of a suitable building for the accommodation of the same, and for the use of charitable societies." In 1864, the organization changed its name to the American Congregational Association in recognition of its broader scope.
The Association lived in peripatetic existence until 1898. In 1857 the Association moved from its rented rooms at the Tremont Temple to a house on Chauncy Street where it remained for ten years. Between 1867 and 1872, the Association again rented space before purchasing two buildings at the corner of Beacon and Somerset Streets. The building was renovated for library space and rental offices. This new headquarters was dedicated in 1874. The Association moved once more, in 1898, to its present site in the Congregational House at 14 Beacon Street, Boston, Massachusetts, a building constructed specifically for the library and for rental office space. Throughout its history, the American Congregational Association prioritized renting space to non-profit organizations.
In 2017 the American Congregational Association sold the Congregational House to Faros Properties and signed a long-term lease to keep the library within its historic home.
Scope and Contents
This collection is the internal permanent archive of the American Congregational Association, and by relation, the Congregational Library & Archives. The collection covers the four main areas of business of the American Congregational Association: The Board of Directors, the Finances of the Association, the management of the Association's building portfolio, and the management of the Congregational Library & Archives. The collection contains minutes of meetings, important financial and tax records, committee records, records related to construction projects, architectural drawings, business proposals and reports, photographs and audio-visual materials, correspondence, management records, and records relating to the functions of the Congregational Library & Archives and its collections.
Arrangement
This collection has been divided into five series, four of which have been further divided into subseries. Four of the series are related to the four main areas of business of the American Congregational Association: The Board of Directors, the Finances of the Association, the management of the Association's building portfolio, and the management of the Congregational Library & Archives. The fifth series contains visual and audio-visual materials. Materials within each series, and the subseries themselves, have been arranged primarily by chronological order and secondarily by topic, when appropriate.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series 1:
Board of directors records, 1851-1822
Subseries 1:
Meeting records, 1851-2022
Subseries 2:
Correspondence, 1851-2008
Subseries 3:
Governance records, 1854-2014
Subseries 4:
Historical records, 1855-2003
Subseries 5:
Board members, 1886-2014
Subseries 6:
Finance and budget committee records, 1872-2006
Subseries 7:
Ad-hoc committee records, 1872-2007
Subseries 8:
Library committee records, 1901-2011
Subseries 9:
Executive committee records, 1929-1999
Subseries 10:
Investment committee records, 1969-2009
Subseries 11:
Treasurer's reports, 1970-1996
Subseries 12:
Personnel committee records, 1999-2009
Subseries 13:
Board development committee records, 1999-2010
Subseries 14:
Development committee records, 1999-2022
Subseries 15:
Program committee records, 2000-2008
Subseries 16:
Building committee records, 2000-2009
Series 2:
Financial records, 1851-2021
Subseries 1:
Ledgers and receipts, 1851-2019
Subseries 2:
Membership and subscriptions, 1853-2001
Subseries 3:
Correspondence, 1871-1977
Subseries 4:
Tax and audit records, 1924-2021
Series 3:
Building records, 1846-2019
Subseries 1:
Financial records, 1846-2012
Subseries 2:
Assessments and reports, 1871-2019
Subseries 3:
Building history, 1872-1998
Subseries 4:
Correspondence, 1872-2005
Subseries 5:
Tenancy and rents, 1873-2010
Subseries 6:
Architectural drawings, 1897-2019
Subseries 7:
Building management records, 1897-2011
Subseries 8:
Renovations and construction projects, 1897-2016
Subseries 9:
Sale of the building records, 1927-2018
Series 4:
Congregational Library & Archives, 1853-2022
Subseries 1:
General correspondence, 1853-2004
Subseries 2:
Library and archives records, 1854-2016
Subseries 3:
Development records, 1856-2008
Subseries 4:
Communications, 1859-2022
Subseries 5:
Collections, 1853-2004
Subseries 6:
Researcher and reference correspondence, 1897-2004
Subseries 7:
Congregational Christian Historical Society records, 1951-2008
Subseries 8:
Facilities, 1963-2020
Series 5:
Photographic and audio-visual materials, 1953-2013, undated
Technical Requirements
Audio-visual materials require specific equipment for playback.
Account books.; Architecture -- Designs and plans; Articles of incorporation.; Boards of directors; Building management; By-laws; Congregationalism.; Contracts for deeds; Corporate governance.; Corporate minutes.; Fund raising; Libraries and institutions; Library finance; Nonprofit organizations; Office buildings; Photographs.; Real estate management; Religious libraries; Research libraries; American Congregational Association.; Congregational Christian Historical Society; Congregational Library Association.; Langworthy, Isaac P. (Isaac Pendleton); Worthley, Harold Field
- Board of directors records, 1851 2022; 1851-2022; 309 Folders; 8 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the board of directors of the American Congregational Association. This series contains the meeting minutes of the board of directors as well as the various committees of the board of directors. This series also contains various governance related documents, such as by-laws and incorporation documents. Financial records may also be found within the treasurer's reports as well as within the general board records. The majority of records within this series are meeting minutes, but reports, proposals, and correspondence also make up a significant portion of the series.
  - Meeting records, 1851 2022; 1851-2022; 64 Folders; 3 Volumes
    This subseries contains the records and minutes of meetings held by the full board of directors of the American Congregational Association. While the bulk of the materials within the subseries are minutes and departmental reports, the subseries also contains correspondence, proposals, and financial records.
    - Association record book, 1851 1853; 1851-1853 (Box 5, Volume 1)
    - Association record book, 1863 1887; 1863-1887 (Box 6, Volume 1)
    - Association record book, 1887 1928; 1887-1928 (Box 6, Volume 2)
    - Annual meetings, 1928 1935; 1928-1935 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Annual meetings, 1936 1944; 1936-1944 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Annual meetings, 1945 1954; 1945-1954 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Annual meetings, 1955 1962; 1955-1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Annual meetings, 1963 1970; 1963-1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Annual meetings, 1969 1970; 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Quarterly meetings, 1928 1934; 1928-1934 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Quarterly meetings, 1935 1941; 1935-1941 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Quarterly meetings, 1942 1950; 1942-1950 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Quarterly meetings, 1950 1955; 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Quarterly meetings, 1956 1962; 1956-1962 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Quarterly meetings, 1963 1970; 1963-1970 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Board of directors meetings, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2019 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2020 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2021 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Board of directors meetings, 2022 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1851 2008; 1851-2008; 19 Folders
    This subseries contains correspondence from, and with, the board of directors of the American Congregational Association.
    - Correspondence, 1851 1855; 1851-1855 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Joseph S. Clark correspondence, A-G, 1853 1854; 1853-1854 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Joseph S. Clark correspondence, H-O, 1853 1854; 1853-1854 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Joseph S. Clark correspondence, P-W, 1853 1854; 1853-1854 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Joseph S. Clark correspondence, 1854 1857; 1854-1857 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Congregational Library Association correspondence, 1855 1859; 1855-1859 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Isaac P. Langworthy correspondence, 1857 1870; 1857-1870, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Joseph S. Clark correspondence, 1860 1866; 1860-1866 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Congregational Library Association correspondence, 1862 1865; 1862-1865 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1867 1884; 1867-1884 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Letters from the board, 1870 1899; 1870-1899 (Box 15, Folder 55)
    - Albert Dunning correspondence, 1908 1917; 1908-1917 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Thomas Todd correspondence, 1913 1917; 1913-1917 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Congregational Library Association correspondence, 1932 2008; 1932-2008 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Harold Worthley board correspondence, 1979 1987; 1979-1987 (Box 15, Folder 56)
    - Harold Worthley board correspondence, 1988 1989; 1988-1989 (Box 15, Folder 57)
    - Harold Worthley board correspondence, 1997 2002; 1997-2002 (Box 15, Folder 58)
    - Harold Worthley board correspondence, 2002 2003; 2002-2003 (Box 15, Folder 59)
    - Harold Worthley board correspondence, 2002 2003; 2002-2003 (Box 15, Folder 60)
  - Governance records, 1854 2014; 1854-2014; 15 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the governance of the American Congregational Association and its board of directors. This subseries contains mission statements, board books, by-laws, and the association's acts of incorporation.
    - Copy of act of incorporation, 1854 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Copy of an act of incorporation, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 38)
    - Acts of incorporation and by-laws, 1864 1969; 1864-1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - By-law revisions, 1926 1929; 1926-1929 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - By-laws, 1992 1999; 1992-1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Library mission statement, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 49)
    - Mission statements, 1996 2001; 1996-2001 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Missions statements, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 50)
    - American Congregationalism Association handbook, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - American Congregationalism Association handbook, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - By-law revisions, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - American Congregationalism Association handbooks, 2009 2012; 2009-2012 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - By-laws, 2009 2010; 2009-2010 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - By-law revisions, 2010 2014; 2010-2014 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Restated articles of organization, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Historical records, 1855 2003; 1855-2003; 9 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the history of the American Congregational Association. Most of this subseries is related to various anniversaries of the association.
    - Second anniversary leaflet, 1855 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Charles Sherman complaint, 1901 (Box 15, Folder 48)
    - 50th anniversary correspondence and program, 1903 (Box 15, Folder 61)
    - 100th anniversary records, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 62)
    - Anniversaries and histories, 1953 2003; 1953-2003 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Board highlights 1853-1900, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - 125th anniversary program, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 63)
    - 100th anniversary display, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 64)
    - 150th anniversary celebration, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 65)
  - Board members, 1886 2014; 1886-2014; 9 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to specific board members.
    - James White resignation, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Thomas Todd Jr., 1898 2007; 1898-2007, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Board members activities, 1908 1975; 1908-1975 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Board members assignments and resignations, 1955 2014; 1955-2014 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Arvel M. Steece, 1959 2015; 1959-2015 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Thomas Todd Jr. papers, 1966 1969; 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Life memberships and honorary directors, 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Burdette Johnson, 1980 2005; 1980-2005 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Board members activities, 1983 1999; 1983-1999 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Finance and budget committee records, 1872 2006; 1872-2006; 8 Folders
    This subseries contains records created by, and for, the finance and budget committee of the American Congregational Association. The finance and budget committee was created to provide board oversight of the association's finances and budget processes. The bulk of the records are meeting minutes.
    - Finance committee report, circa 1872 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Finance and budget committee records, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Finance and budget committee records, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Finance and budget committee records, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Finance and budget committee records, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Finance and budget committee records, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Finance and budget committee records, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Finance and budget committee records, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Ad-hoc committee records, 1872 2007; 1872-2007; 18 Folders; 3 Volumes
    This subseries contains the records of various ad-hoc committees formed for the American Congregational Association throughout its history. The bulk of the records contained within this subseries are meeting minutes.
    - Executive committee for the fair, 1872 (Box 15, Volume 1)
    - Executive committee for the fair daybook, 1872 (Box 16, Volume 4)
    - Miscellaneous committee reports, 1874 1897; 1874-1897 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Building and house committee, 1895 1896; 1895-1896 (Box 15, Folder 51)
    - Joint building and house committee minutes, 1897 (Box 15, Volume 2)
    - Building and house committee, 1897 1900; 1897-1900 (Box 15, Folder 52)
    - Rare Book Room construction committee, 1962 1966; 1962-1966 (Box 15, Folder 53)
    - Financial appeals task force sub-committee records, 1993 1994; 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Budget review sub-committee records, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Long-range planning committee records, 1995 1996; 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Development / anniversary committee records, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Board restructure committee records, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Visitors center committee records, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Visitors center committee records, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Visitors center committee records, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Vision steering committee records, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Vision steering committee records, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Vision steering committee records, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Alternate partners committee records, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Strategic planning committee records, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Possibility planning group records, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Library committee records, 1938 2011; 1901-2011; 45 Folders; 2 Volumes
    This subseries contains records created by, and for, the library committee of the American Congregational Association. The library committee was created to provide board oversight the functions of the Congregational Library & Archives. The bulk of the records are meeting minutes, though presentations, proposals, and reports to the library committee are also included.
    - Library committee daybook, 1901 1917; 1901-1917 (Box 15, Volume 3)
    - Library committee minutes, 1938 1954; 1938-1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Library committee minutes, 1954 1967; 1954-1967 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      Separated Materials
      This folder was partially created out of loose materials which were originally interleaved in the volume labeled "Library Committee minutes, 1957-1967". The original order of the contents of the folder has been maintained.
    - Library committee minutes, 1957 1967; 1957-1967 (Box 3, Volume 1)
      Loose materials interleaved within this volume were removed for preservation purposes and placed in the folder labeled "Library committee minutes, 1954-1967".
    - Library committee records, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Library committee records, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Library committee records, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Library committee records, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Library committee records, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Library committee records, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Library committee records, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Library committee librarian search, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 54)
    - Library committee records, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Library committee records, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Library committee records, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Library committee records, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Library committee records, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Library committee records, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Library committee records, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Library committee records, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Library committee records, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Library committee records, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Library committee records, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Library committee records, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Library committee records, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Library committee records, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Library committee records, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Library committee records, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Library committee records, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Library committee records, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Library committee records, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Library committee records, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Library committee records, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Library committee records, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Library committee records, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Library committee records, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Library committee records, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Library committee records, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 62)